现在我们已经讲完了信息完整性
Now that we're done with message
integrity, we're gonna back and talk about
【伊卡酱 译注】
我们将回到加密的讨论，我们将展示如何构建加密机制
encryption, and we're gonna show how to
construct encryption schemes that provide
提供比之前强得多的安全性
much stronger security guarantees than
what we had before. But first let's do a
首先，我们回顾一下。在前面的内容里，我们讨论了私密性
recap of where we are. So in previous
segments, we talked about confidentiality,
特别地，如何加密信息，让我们获得语义安全
in particular how to encrypt messages such
that we achieve semantic security against
来对抗选择明文攻击。现在我一再提到
what's called a chosen plaintext attack.
Now I kept mentioning again and again that
对选择明文攻击的安全性仅仅提供了
security against chosen plaintext attacks
only provides security against
对抗窃听的安全性。换句话说，这仅仅提供了
eavesdropping. In other words, this only
provides security against adversaries that
对抗只会监听网络流量的攻击者的安全性，
但攻击者不会改变任何数据包
listen to network traffic. But don't
actually change any packets, or don't
也不会篡改数据包，等等。本章中，我们的目标是
inject their own packets, and so on. In
this module, our goal is actually to
设计加密机制，以对抗可以篡改信息的攻击者
design encryption schemes that are secure
against adversaries that can tamper with
攻击者可以封锁特定的数据包，以及修改其他的数据包等
traffic by blocking certain packets, and
injecting other packets and so on. And
然后我们看了如何提供信息完整性，信息本身不是私密的
then we also looked at how to provide
message integrity where the message itself
我们只想确保信息在传输中没被修改
is not confidential. We just want to make
sure that the message is not modified
我们讨论了信息验证码MAC
while it's en route. And so we talked
about message authentication codes, MAC
MAC算法对选择信息攻击提供了不可存在性伪造的性质
algorithms that provide existential
unforgeability against a chosen message
换句话说，尽管攻击者可以获得他选择的
attack. In other words, even though the
attacker is able to obtain the MACs on
信息的MAC，他也不能构建其他信息的MAC
arbitrary messages of his choice, he can't
build MACs for any other messages. And we
我们看了很多MAC机制，特别是CBC-MAC, HMAC
looked at a number of MAC constructions,
in particular CBC MAC, HMAC, a Parallel MAC
并行MAC，一个快速MAC机制叫做Carter-Wegman MAC
construction. And a fast MAC construction
called a Carter-Wegman MAC. In this
本章中，我们将展示如何把私密性和完整性机制组合起来
module, we're going to show how to combine
these confidentiality and integrity
得到的加密机制可以对抗
mechanisms to obtain encryption schemes
that are secure against a much, much
强大得多的攻击者，即攻击者可以修改网络通信内容
stronger adversary, namely an adversary that
can tamper with traffic while it's in the
感染数据包，封锁特定数据包等等
network, inject its own packets, block
certain packets, and so on. And our goal
我们的目标是确保即使对抗如此强大的攻击者
is basically to insure that even against
such powerful adversaries, we maintain
我们依然可以保持私密性。换句话说，攻击者
confidentiality. In other words, the
adversary can't learn what the plain text
无法学习到明文内容，无法修改密文
is and the adversary can't even modify the
cipher text and cause the recipient to
并让接收方对经过修改后的明文信以为真。那么在这之前
think a different plain text was actually
sent. So before we do that I want to give
我想给大家一个攻击者的例子，他们可以篡改通信
you a few examples of adversaries that can
tamper with traffic. And as a result
因此完全破坏了CPA安全加密的安全性。这个会告诉大家
completely break security of CPA secure
encryption. This will show you that,
实际上那种方法提供的完整性和私密性也会被破坏
actually, with that providing integrity,
confidentiality can also be destroyed. In
换句话说，完整性和私密性，两者必须都保证
other words, the two must go together,
integrity and confidentiality, if we're
如果我们要安全地对抗主动型攻击者
going to achieve security against active
adversaries. So let's look at an example
那我们看个网络领域的例子。特别地，我们看TCP/IP
from the world of networking. In
particular, let's look at TCP/IP. I'm gonna
我使用一个高度简化的TCP/IP版本，这样我们可以
use a highly simplified version of TCP/IP
just so we can quickly focus on the attack
关注于攻击，不拘泥于细节。我们有两个机器互相通信
and not get bogged down by the details. So
here we have two machines communicating
一用户坐在一台机器上，另一台机器是个服务器
with one another. A user sits at one
machine, and the other machine is a
现在，服务器上当然有TCP/IP协议栈在接收数据包
server. Now, the server, of course, has a
TCP/IP stack that's receiving packets. And
然后，根据这些数据包的目标地址域，服务器把数据包
then, based on the destination field in
those packets, it forwards the packets to
转发到合适的位置。比如，这里我们有两个进程
the appropriate place. So here we have,
for example, two processes listening to
在监听这些数据包。一个网页服务器在这里。
另一个用户，我们叫他Bob
these packets. A web server, say, over
here, and another user, we'll call him
Bob在这里。网页服务器监听80端口
Bob, over here. The web server listens on
port 80, and here, this user Bob, listens
这个用户Bob监听25端口。现在，当一个数据包到来时，
TCP/IP协议栈查看目标端口
on port 25. Now, when a packet comes in,
the TCP/IP stack looks at the destination
在这个情况下，端口号是80，因此
port. In this case, it would be
destination 80, and as a result, the stack
协议栈把数据包转发到网页服务器。如果目标端口是25
forwards the packets over to the web
server. If the destination port said port
TCP/IP协议栈会把数据包转发给Bob
25, the TCP/IP stack would forward the
packet over to Bob, who's listening on
Bob在监听25端口。现在，一个很有名的安全协议叫做IPsec
port 25. Now, a fairly well known security
protocol called IPsec, encrypts these IP
加密了发送方和接收方之间的IP数据包
packets between the sender and the
recipient. So here, the sender and the
这里，发送方和接收方共享一个密钥。
当发送方发送IP数据包时
recipients basically have a shared key.
And when the sender sends IP packets,
使用密钥K来加密这些IP包。现在一个数据包
those IP packets are encrypted using the
secret key K. Now when a packet arrives at
到达了目的地，我的意思是到达了服务器
the destination, and I mean it arrives at
the server, the TCP/IP stack will go ahead
TCP/IP栈会解密这个数据包，然后看目标端口
and decrypt the packet, and then look at
the destination port and send it to the
把数据包发送到合适的位置去解密。大家注意，
这里的数据是被加密的
appropriate place decrypted. You notice
the data here is decrypted. So in this
这种情况下，会把数据发给网页服务器，
因为目标端口是80
case it would send it to the webserver
because the destination port is port 80.
如果目标端口正好是25，TCP/IP栈会解密这个包
If the destination port happens to be port
25, the TCP/IP stack will decrypt the
看目标端口，然后把明文数据发给相应进程
packet, look at the destination port, and
send the data in the clear to the process
这个进程正监听25端口。现在我想告诉大家，没有完整性的话
who's listening on port 25. So now I wanna
show you that without integrity, in this
这里我们不能获得任何的私密性，我们来看为什么
setup, we can't possibly achieve any form
of confidentiality and let's see why. So
想像一下攻击者截获了一个特定的给网页服务器的数据包
imagine the attacker intercepts a certain
packet that's intended for the web server.
换句话说，这是个加密的目标端口为80的数据包
In other words, it's an encrypted packet
intended for port 80. Remember that the
攻击者实际上可以接收任何给25端口的数据包的解密
attacker can actually receive the
decryption of any packets that's intended
因为TCP协议栈会乐意解密给25端口的数据包
for port 25 because the TCP stack will
happily decrypt packets for port 25 and
并把结果给正在监听的Bob。这里Bob是攻击者
send them over to Bob who's listening over
here. So what Bob is going to do, Bob here
他会截获途中的数据包
is the attacker, what he's going to do is
he's gonna intercept this packet en route,
防止数据包到达服务器
prevent the packet from reaching the
server as is, and instead, he's going to
而他将修改这个数据包。现在目标端口读起来是25了
modify the packet. So now the destination
port is going to read like port 25. This
这在密文里完成，我们待会将看到怎么办
is done on the cipher text and we're going
to see how to do that in just a minute.
当这个数据包到达服务器时，目标端口说是25
When this packet now arrives at the
server, the destination port says 25, the
服务器会解密这个数据包，看到目标端口是25
server will decrypt the packet, see that
the destination is 25 and forward the data
就把数据转发给了Bob。现在Bob通过改变目标端口
over to Bob. So now Bob was simply by
changing the destination ports, Bob was
就可以读到本不该给他的数据
able to read data that was not intended
for himself, but rather was intended for
这数据应该是给网页服务器的。如果数据是使用
带随机IV的CBC加密的
the web server. So, if the data is
encrypted using a CBC encryption with a
记得这是一个对CPA安全的机制。不过如果是这种情况
random IV, remember this is a CPA secure
scheme. Nevertheless if that's the case,
我将为大家展示，攻击者很容易改变密文
I'm gonna show you that it's trivial for
the attacker to change the cipher text.
以获得新密文，其目标端口是25，而非80
So that now he can obtain new cipher text
where the destination port is 25 instead
攻击者只需要修改IV域即可。事实上
of 80. The only thing that's gonna change
is just the IV field. In fact, everything
其他的一切都保持不变。那么，我们看怎么办
else is gonna remain the same. So, let's
see how to do it. So here, just to remind
记住，事实上，攻击者捕捉的是一个CBC加密的数据包
yourself, that, in fact, what the attacker
captured is a CBC encrypted packet. Where
从这个数据包里，攻击者知道了目标端口是80，
但他不知道数据是什么
he knows that the destination port is port
80, but he doesn't know what the data is.
攻击者没有关于数据内容的任何线索，
但他知道这个数据包是给网页服务器的
The attacker has no clue what the data is
but he does know that his packet is
他的目标是构建一个新的加密的数据包
intended for the web server. His goal is
to build a new encrypted packet where now
其目标端口是25。我们说过，攻击者只需
the destination port is port 25. So the
way he's gonna do is as we said is just by
改变IV，让我提醒大家，解密CBC加密的数据的方法是
changing the IV, and let me remind you that
the way you decrypt CBC encrypted data is
本质上，第一个明文分组是第一个密文分组
essentially the first plain text block is
simply decryption of the first cipher
与IV异或结果的解密。我们知道在原数据包里
text block XORed with IV. And we
know that in the original packet this is
这会读到目标端口为80。因为在原数据包中
gonna read dest equals 80. Cuz in the
original packet the destination port is
目标端口是80。现在我给大家的问题是，
攻击者该如何修改IV
port 80. So now my question to you is how
will the attacker have changed the IV so
使得目标端口读起来是25。容易看出
now the destination port will read dest
equals 25. So it's pretty easy to see that
如果攻击者取原IV，和这个异或
if the attacker simply takes the original
IV, XORs it with here, there are a bunch
这里有很多0，这里也有很多0。攻击者异或了很多0
of zeros over here, and a bunch of zeros
over here. He's XORs it with the zeros,
然后80异或0，然后是25，在合适的地方
and then 80 XORs with zeros, and then 25,
in the appropriate place. Namely, in the
也就是在加密的数据包的端口域字节里。
然后容易看出这个新的IV'
port's bytes in the encrypted packets. Then
it's easy to see that when this new IV prime
与原密文信息一并发送，当攻击者解密时
is sent along with the original
cipher text, when the attacker decrypts,
大家可以看到原密文会解密到80端口
you can see that the original cipher text
would decrypt to port 80, but now the new
但现在这个新的IV会抵消掉这个80，这个80
把本该从原明文中获得的80抵消掉了
IV will cancel out this 80, this 80 here
cancels out the 80 that would be obtained
然后通过与25异或
in the original plain text and then by
XORing with 25, essentially the
目标端口现在变成25了。那么这是一个很好的例子
destination now becomes 25. So this is a
nice example, where with the simple change
通过简单修改IV域，攻击者可以重定向数据包
to the IV field, the attacker was able to
divert the packet. So that now, after
现在，在解密后，数据包将送给攻击者，而不是网页服务器
decryption, the packet goes to the
attacker, instead of the actual web
因此，现在攻击者能读到明文数据
server. And as a result now the attacker
can read the plaintext data, that was
这些本应给服务器的。这个好例子展示了
intended for the server. So this nice
example shows that without integrity it's
没有完整性，一个CPA安全的加密不可能提供私密性
simply impossible for a CPA secure
encryption to provide confidentiality,
如果攻击者可以在途中修改数据包
when the attacker can modify packets
en route. CPA secure encryption only
CPA安全加密只能在攻击者只能窃听数据的
这一假设下，提供私密性
provides confidentiality if the attacker is
only eavesdropping on data, but can't
但攻击者不能在途中修改密文。大家看到
actually modify a cipher text en route.
Where, as you see, if you can modify
如果你可以修改密文，一个简单的修改，也会完全改变明文
cipher text, a simple modification,
completely reveals the plaintext. I want
我想给大家看另外一个篡改攻击的例子，
只需要能接收到网络流量即可
to show you another tampering attack that
only requires network access to traffic.
不需要攻击者在解密机器上操作
It doesn't actually require the attacker
to be present on the decryption machine.
我们再看一个例子，有一个远程终端的应用
So let's look at an example where there's
a remote terminal application, where every
每次用户敲击键盘，一个加密的键盘输入被送往服务器
time the user hits a keystroke, basically
an encrypted keystroke is sent over to the
我们假定键盘输入是使用计数器模式加密的
server, and let's pretend that the
encrypted keystroke is encrypted using
这里你有TCP/IP包。这里D对应一个字节输入
counter mode. So here you have the
TCP/IP packet. D here corresponds to the
我们说过，它是使用计数器模式加密的
one byte keystroke. And as we said, it's
encrypted using counter mode, and as you
大家大概知道，每个TCP/IP包包含了一个校验和
probably know every TCP/IP packet actually
contains a checksum. This is a sixteen bit
校验和只能使用于检测传输错误
checksum that's just used to detect
transmission errors. So, the server, if it
如果服务器接收了一个含错误校验和的数据包，
它就会简单地扔了这个包
receives a packet that has the wrong
checksum, it simply drops it on the floor
忽略它。现在TCP报文头包含了键盘输入的校验和
and ignores it. Now the TCP header
including the checksum in the keystroke,
所有都是用计数器模式加密的。现在攻击者想学习
键盘输入的内容
all are encrypted using counter mode. Now
the attacker wants to learn what the
我来告诉大家他会怎么做。攻击者会截获这个数据包
keystroke was, and let me show you what he
can do. The attacker is gonna intercept
他不修改它，直接把包发给服务器
this packet and he's not actually gonna
modify it, he's gonna send it over to the
但他会记录下这个数据包。之后他将修改数据包
server. But he's gonna record the packet.
Later on he's gonna modify the packet and
然后把修改后的数据包发给服务器。
send a modified packet over to the server.
What he's going to do is he's gonna XOR
他会把加密的校验和和一个值T异或
the encrypted checksum field with a
value T and he's going to XOR the
他会把加密的数据和一个值S异或。
他用很多的T和S来做这件事
encrypted data field with a value S. And
he's going to do this for lots and lots of
现在，记得计数器模式的一个性质是
T and S. Now remember, a property
of counter mode is that if you XOR the
如果你用T异或密文，解密后明文结果也是与T异或的
cipher text with T, after decryption, the
result in plain text is also XOR with T.
类似地，如果你用S异或加密数据，解密后
Similarly, if you XOR the encrypted data with S, after decryption.
获得的解密数据也是与S异或后的
the resulting decrypted data will also be
encrypted with S. Now, the server's gonna
(口误：encrypted->XORed)
服务器解密这个修改后的数据包，得到的数据包
decrypt this modified packet. And the
resulting packet is gonna have the
有个异或了T的校验和，而数据是异或了S的
checksum XORed with T, and the data XORed with S. Now what happens if the
如果修改的校验和对于这个修改的数据包来说是正确的，
服务器会发送一个ACK应答包
modified checksum is correct for this
modified packet, the server will send an
如果修改后的校验和对于修改后的数据包来说不正确
ACK back. If the modified checksum
is incorrect for this modified packet, the
服务器会扔掉这个数据包，什么也不做
server will just drop the packet on the
floor and do nothing. So the attacker can
所以攻击者可以观察到，看看能不能收到ACK包
simply observe, look for an ACK packet or
not, and in doing so, he learns whether
这样他能学习到特定的T异或和S异或，
是否对应一个有效的校验和
this particular XOR of T and XOR of S
pairs corresponds to a valid checksum or not.
现在攻击者要对很多T和S做这件事
Now the attacker's going to do
this for lots and lots of T's and S's.
大家注意到攻击者会学习到，如果我修改了数据，
把数据和特定值S异或
And you notice what he learns is if I
modify the data by XORing it with this
那么校验和就要与T异或
particular value S, that changes the
checksum by a particular value T. And
他学到了很多的T和S
he learns this for lots and lots of T and
S pairs. So it turns out for certain
对特定的校验和，看一系列这样的方程
checksums, by looking at a sequence of
equations of this type. You can actually
你可以解出值D。我应该指出对于这里的TCP校验和
figure out what the value D is. I should
point out that for the TCP checksums on this,
可能是错误的。但当然它们是简单的校验和
actually, might not be true. But
certainly, they're easy checksums for
这里是完全正确的。再看很多这样的方程
which this is actually absolutely true. So
again by looking at a lot of equations of
攻击者可以恢复D。这是一个很好的例子
this type the attacker can recover D. And
this is a really nice example of what's
被叫做选择密文攻击。攻击者提交他选择的密文
called a chosen cipher text attack. The
attacker basically submitted cipher text
是由他想解密的密文所推出的
of his choice that was derived from that
cipher text that he wanted to decrypt. And
然后看服务器如何反应，攻击者可以学习到
then by looking at how the server
responded he was able to learn something
明文的一些信息。重复这个操作，用许多不同的T和S值
about the resulting plaint text. And by
repeating this for many different values
攻击者最终可以还原整个明文
of T and S he was actually eventually able to
recover what the actual full plain text is.
本节，我们将看许多这种攻击的例子
So in this segment we are gonna look
at many more examples of attacks of this
它们叫做主动攻击，攻击者可修改途中的通信
type. These are called active attacks,
where the attackers actually modify
我希望这两个简单的例子可以说服大家
traffic in route. And I hope that these
two simple example convinces you that all
只提供CPA安全，或者说对抗窃听的安全
you provide is CPA security, in other words
security against eavesdropping. You can't
对抗主动攻击者时不能保证安全
even guarantee secrecy against an active
attacker. Not only does your cipher text
不仅密文没有完整性，换句话说，接收方可能收到
not have integrity, in other words the
recipients might obtain a message
一个与发送方所发出的不同的信息；
而且甚至连私密性也没有
different from the one sent by the sender.
But you don't even have confidentiality.
我为大家展示了两个例子，其中没有完整性
And I showed you two examples where
without integrity the attacker can simply
攻击者就可以把接收方当成一个神谕，来解密数据包
decrypt the packet by using the recipient
as an oracle for decrypting certain parts
(神谕：可以回答特定的询问，大量节省询问者的计算)
神谕负责解密数据的特定部分。
这个教训我要在本章中反复强调
of the data. And so the lesson that I'm
gonna repeat again and again and again
如果你的信息需要完整性，但不需要私密性
throughout this module is that if your
message needs integrity but no
使用MAC就够了。但如果你的信息需要完整性
confidentiality, just use a MAC. But if
your message needs integrity and
同时也要私密性，那你必须使用一个认证加密模式
confidentiality, you have to use what's
called an authenticated encryption mode,
也就是本章的主题。接下来
which is precisely the topic of this
module. So the next thing we're gonna do
我们定义认证加密的意义
is define what authenticated encryption
means. And we're gonna build authenticated
我们要构建认证加密系统。但这里我希望大家记住
encryption systems. But the point I want
you to remember is that the CPA security
我们之前讨论过的CPA安全模式，
不应当被使用在加密数据上
modes we discussed before should never
actually be used to encrypt data by
带随机IV的CBC可以为认证加密构建分组
themselves. So CBC with a random IV is a
building block towards authenticated
但不应被单独使用
encryption, but should never be used on
its own. Okay. So we're gonna define
下一节我们定义认证加密
authenticated encryption in the next
segment.